Alright, בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is דף ה. daf
hey. We pick up
on ד עמוד ב, daled amud bet, what were we a little
bit behind, we'll try to correct that,
and we are near the two lines before the lines get wide
with the two dots. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, so about
ten lines from the bottom of ד עמוד ב. daled amud bet.
And the גמרא Gemara is in the middle of some digressions because
it had been talking about how late you say שמע Shema
and so actually not such a digression but we were talking about
the issue about when at night for דאווען שמנה עשרה daven Shemoneh
Esrei, and then say שמע Shema or do you first say שמע
Shema and then דאווען daven שמנה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei the order and
the idea of putting שמע Shema right before, juxtaposing שמע Shema and
שמנה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, סמוך גאולה לתפילה. somech geulah letfillah. Just one
final comment about that, the גמרא Gemara ended by saying though at
night we don't always do it precisely because we have a second
ברכה Bracha that intervened between the end of שמע Shema and the
beginning of שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei to the concept of גאולה אריכתא,
geulah arichta, extended גאולה geulah in the sense that once the Rabbis
made it part of the liturgy and this ברכה Bracha השכיבנו Hashkivenu
after שמע Shema is also part of the liturgy even though it's
not on the theme of גאולה, geulah, that becomes incorporated and therefore
still seen as a juxtaposition. And based on that we did explain
that this is going to be an ongoing issue around seeing שמע
Shema as the מצוה mitzvah of שמע Shema that happens to be
done in the morning and
the afternoon or during דאווען daven or whether it becomes so transformed
as part of the liturgy and then the shape that it takes
on once it's embedded within the liturgy. I should also mention that
תוספות Tosfos points out that we even distance שמע Shema from שמנה
עשרה Shemoneh Esrei even more at nighttime at מעריב Maariv because we
and we don't do it here in this שול shul but in
many places outside of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they have a third
ברכה, Bracha, very long ברכה Bracha ברוך ה' לעולם, Baruch Hashem Le'olam,
and that was done primarily because when people were דאווען daven and
they would דאווען daven in the שולן shuls outside in the fields,
we sort of alluded to that before we'll allude to it again,
you didn't want people finishing up דאווען daven going home and then
people who came late would be left all alone there out in
the fields and they'd have to walk home alone. So they put
in this whole extra ברכה Bracha so to give everybody a chance
to sort of catch up. Also that long extra ברכה Bracha ברוך
ה' לעולם Baruch Hashem Le'olam also has eighteen names of God and
is sort of like almost a mini שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei in
itself. Anyway תוספות Tosfos points out that that too is in principle
a problem of not juxtaposing שמע Shema and שמנה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei,
but again once it becomes part of the liturgy that becomes seen
as an extended גאולה, geulah, that becomes acceptable. Okay now we continue
with the גמרא, Gemara, also continuing also to talk interestingly about liturgical
issues, דאווען daven issues, not exactly שמע, Shema, two lines before the
lines get wide, ד עמוד ב. daled amud bet. אמר רבי אלעזר
אמר רבי אבינא, Amar Rabbi Elazar amar Rabbi Avina, Rabbi Elazar says
in the name of Rabbi Avina, כל אומר תהלה לדוד בכל יום,
kol omer Tehillah LeDavid bechol yom, anybody that says תהלה לדוד Tehillah
LeDavid every day, which we would call by another name what would
we call it? אשרי, Ashrei, אשרי Ashrei every day, right we actually
add two פסוקים psukim before תהלה לדוד Tehillah LeDavid which is actually
where that פרק perek of תהלים Tehillim begins, אשרי Ashrei is actually
an additional פסוק pasuk that we add before that.
Everybody says that שלש פעמים, shalosh pe'amim, three times each day, מובטח
לו שהוא בן עולם הבא, muvtach lo shehu ben olam habah, can
be assured that they are meriting the world to come. Wow so
now we know why we say it three times, what are the
three times we say it?
Twice in the morning.
Very good, I wanted to see if anybody was going to say
שחרית מנחה מעריב Shacharit Mincha Maariv which would not be true, we
don't say it at מעריב. Maariv. רש״י Rashi does say the three
times corresponds to morning, afternoon, and evening, but we say it twice
in the morning, once in the afternoon. Why is it so important?
מאי טעמא, Mai tama, why is it? אילימא משום דאיתא באלף בית,
Ilemah mishum de'isa be'alef bet, it's the אלף בית, alef bet, now
why should the אלף בית alef bet be so significant? I mean
it's a good mnemonic, a lot of תהלים Tehillim are written in
the אלף בית, alef bet, but presumably because somehow you're saying תהלים
Tehillim in the אלף בית alef bet sort of denotes the idea,
expresses the idea that these praises are from the very beginning to
the very end. Thank you. So you know from A to Z,
so it's a way of giving of implicitly sort of praising God
from you know in with all the praises. So if that's what's
significant, so נימא אשרי תמימי דרך, neima Ashrei Temimei Darech, how about
the פרק perek in תהלים Tehillim that starts with אשרי תמימי דרך,
Ashrei Temimei Darech, דאיתא בתמניא אפין d'isa betamnaya alpin that has eight
times, you know, if you actually looked at the largest פרק perek
in תהלים, Tehillim, it's a huge פרק, perek, it does the אלף
בית alef bet eight times, בתמניא אפין, betamnaya alpin, anyway so it
does it eight. אלא, Ela, so that can't be that alone. משום
דאיתא ביה פותח את ידך mishum de'isa bei poteach et yadecha because
it has the פסוק, pasuk, God you open up your hand ומשביע
לכל חי רצון, umasbia lechol chai ratzon, you provide sustenance for the
entire world, which is obviously the very central thing that God gives
ongoing every day, you know, the means for which all of creation,
not just Jews, not just human beings, but all of creation is
able to live and sustain themselves, so that's so central, that's what
makes it so. Some people actually have the practice when they say
that to like open up their hands, you know, and to sort
of
physically symbolize. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that that's so important,
נמי *nami* הלל הגדול *Hallel Hagadol*, say the הלל *Hallel* that הלל
הגדול *Hallel Hagadol*, which is not the הלל המצרי *Hallel Hamitzri* that
we say on the ימים טובים *Yomim Tovim*, but it's the פסוקים
psukim *psukim* of הלל *Hallel* that we say on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*,
you know, embedded in the פסוקי דזמרה *Pesukei D'zimra*. דכתיב Dechtiv, בי
*dechtiv bei*, it says there, נותן לחם לכל בשר *Nosein lechem l'chol
basar*, it has the same ideas expressed. אלא ela, *Ella*, the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, משום דאית בה תרתי *mishum d'is bei tarti*. Okay,
it's got both. It has this very sort of fundamental expression of
God's beneficence and combined with the concept of אלף-בית *aleph-beis*, which also
expresses that in sort of in its complete totality. So through saying
this, we express this idea about the enormous beneficence of God from
the beginning to the end, providing all creatures with all of their
needs. Now, again, presumably, you know, it's always a question about davening,
who are we saying this for? For us or for God? You
know, I would argue that presumably the significance is that this impresses
it upon us, you know, three times a day, and this tremendous
deep awareness of God's constant providing for us in every way is
what makes this so significant in the sense of בן עולם הבא
*Ben Olam Haba*, that, you know, changes your, hopefully, the way you
think in this world and also for the future. So now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, yes.
I have to just interject that I really believe it's a very
mutual kind of thing. That God needs us, we are saying that
השם *Hashem*
really, believe it or not, I believe needs us
too.
Chose us, needs us, and needs us to say that. So I
really think that it's both. That love is a mutual thing, and
that it goes both ways.
I- I very much appreciate that and we'll have plenty of time
also to talk about that as we get more into the issue
of davening. I think the reason I particularly emphasized it here is
the idea of being rewarded with being a בן עולם הבא *Ben
Olam Haba* to me seems to be more about how- what this
is doing for us, you know, so it's not a general comment
about davening, but I very much appreciate that. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan *Amar Rav
Yochanan*, מפני מה לא נאמר נון באשרי *mipnei mah lo ne'emar nun
b'Ashrei*? If anybody noticed when you say אשרי Ashrei, *Ashrei*, and also
fascinating now it's calling it אשרי *Ashrei*. It's no longer calling it
תהלה לדוד *Tehilla L'David*, which is significant. It shows that that idea
of adding those פסוקים Psukim, *psukim* ahead of time had already been
introduced at a very early stage. The פסוק pasuk *pasuk* of אשרי
יושבי ביתך *Ashrei Yoshvei Veitecha* and actually it became part of the
name of that פרק *perek* of תהלים Tehillim. *Tehillim* or the name
of the way it appeared in the liturgy. So, anyway, why is
there no נון *nun* in that? מפני שיש בו מפלתן של שונאי
ישראל *mipnei sheyesh bo mapalatan shel sonei Yisrael*. Because it has in
it the collapsing, the falling of the enemies of Israel, שונאי ישראל
*sonei Yisrael* is a euphemism which means of Israel, we just don't
want to say it. דכתיב *dechtiv*, because there's another נון *nun* that
indicates something very bad. נפלה לא תוסיף קום בתולת ישראל *Nafla lo
tosif kum besulas Yisrael*. You have fallen, you will no longer rise
up, oh maiden of Israel. So somehow the נון *nun* would have
evoked that idea, that other פסוק pasuk *pasuk* with the נון *nun*.
במערבא מתרצי לה הכי *B'Maarava metartzei lah hachi*. In ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael*, they read the פסוק pasuk? *pasuk* the following way,
this נפלה *Nafla*, they don't want to have a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
to say such a thing like that, so here's how they read
it. נפלה ולא תוסיף לנפול קום בנות ישראל *Nafla v'lo tosif linpol,
kum b'nos Yisrael*. You have fallen, you shall no longer
fall, get up, oh daughter of Israel. So they put the comma
in a very different place in order that even that פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* doesn't say it. Now, again, it's a very unusual answer. Why-
there's so many אלף-בית *aleph-beiss* in all of the Torah, you know,
in all of תהלים Tehillim. *Tehillim*, all of a sudden this one
we have to take out the נון *nun* because it would have
evoked this פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. So, it's a strange answer, I mean,
what exactly that means. Others have, you know, I know other biblical
scholars have different explanations why the נון *nun* is missing, but this
is the answer the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* gives. ואמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק *V'amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak*, אפילו הכי חזר בה דוד וסמכן
ברוח הקודש *afilu hachi chazar bei David u'smachan b'ruach hakodesh*, and maybe
it gave that answer specifically because it has the following thing to
say, that the נון *nun* is missing, but here's the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* that comes after the נון *nun*, the סמך *samech* is, שנאמר
Shene'emar, סומך השם לכל הנופלים *shene'emar Somech Hashem l'chol hanoflim*. God supports
all those that are fallen. So exactly the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* after
where the נון *nun* would have been has God supporting and has
the word נופל *nofel*, those that would have fallen, so therefore that's
why it is missing. Maybe you could even say that maybe the
נון *nun* is embedded in the פסוק Pasuk, *pasuk* of סומך השם
לכל הנופלים *Somech Hashem l'chol hanoflim*, that you have the נפילה *nefila*
but it already is preceded with the idea that God already provides
the support. Okay, so אמר רבי אלעזר בר אבינא Amar Rabbi Elazar
Bar Avina, *Amar Rabbi Elazar bar Avina*, גדול מה שנאמר במיכאל יותר
מה שנאמר בגבריאל Gadol mah shene'emar beMichael yoser mah shene'emar beGabriel. *gadol
mah shene'emar b'Michael yoser mah shene'emar b'Gavriel*. Greater is what is said
about Michael than what is said about Gavriel. I should just also
find one also point about why all of a sudden did it
stick in the אשרי *Ashrei* thing right here after the previous discussion?
And I just do wonder, again, you know, it's always a question
of exactly when our current תפילה *tfila* and the shape it's in
became crystallized. So we had just been talking about preceding, right, שמונה
עשרה Shmoneh Esrei, *Shmonei Esrei* with שמע Shema *Shma*. Well, that covers
you for שחרית *Shacharis* and מעריב Maariv *Maariv*. What about מנחה Mincha.
*Mincha*? So מנחה *Mincha*, you don't precede it with גאולה *Geula*, but
you do precede it with אשרי *Ashrei* as a way that you
don't jump right into שמונה עשרה *Shmonei Esrei*, you sort of build
up to it. So I do wonder, its position here in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, is this suggesting that already at this stage... they
had it situated אשרי before the שמנה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei of מנחה.
Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. Right? I mean, for people
that aren't aware, we're not going to find יבמות Yevamos or ברכות
Berachos explaining okay here's where we do ברכות השחר, Birchos Hashachar, here's
where we do you know
here's where we do פסוקי דזמרא, Psukei Dezimra, here's where we do
זה, zeh, you have little pieces of the liturgy that are sort
of explained primarily שמע Shema. and the ברכות Brachos in שמנה עשרה
Shmoneh Esrei and all the rest it's not really clear when it
sort of got developed, when it got inserted, when it got crystallized
and into that form within the דאווענען. davening. So that's something to
be keeping in mind. Alright now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רבי
אלעזר בר אבינא, Amar Rabbi Elazar Bar Avina גדול מה שנאמר shene'emar
במיכאל יותר מה שנאמר Shene'emar בגבריאל. Greater is that which is said
by Michael than what is said by Gabriel. דאילו במיכאל כתיב, De'ilu
beMichael kesiv, when it comes to Michael it says ויעף אלי אחד
מן השרפים, Vaya'af elay echad min hasrafim,
one of the שרפים Srafim the fire angels flew to me. And
that's ויעף vaya'af once, so it's in one sort of quick jump,
quick you know he flew straight away to me. ואילו גבי גבריאל
כתיב, Ve'ilu gabei Gabriel kesiv, when it talks about the angel Gabriel
כתיב kesiv והאיש גבריאל אשר ראיתי בחזון בתחילה Veha'ish Gabriel asher raisi
bachazon betchila
and the man Gabriel the angel Gabriel that I saw initially in
the vision מעוף ביעף. me'uf bi'af. He was flying to fly, so
the double language מעוף ביעף me'uf bi'af means that it took sort
of two you know jumps to get to me, two flyings not
one. So Michael was even faster than Gabriel. מאי משמע דהאי אחד
מיכאל הוא? Mai mashma dehai echad Michael hu? How do you know
where it says one of the שרפים Srafim it means Michael? So
אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, said רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, אתיא אחד
אחד. Asya echad echad.
You make a link because it says one one. כתיב הכא ויעף
אלי אחד מן השרפים, Kesiv hacha vaya'af elay echad min hasrafim, one
of the שרפים Srafim flew to me, וכתיב התם והנה מיכאל אחד
השרים הראשונים בא לעזרני. Uchsiv hasam vehinei Michael echad hasarim harishonim ba
le'ozreni.
One of the first sort of you know officers but again meaning
angels was coming to help me, again a פסוק Pasuk in דניאל.
Daniel. Okay so again I have no idea what this is doing
here other than it's statements of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan so there's
a couple of a lot of רבי יוחנן statements, so maybe this
is here as well, possibly. רבי אלעזר בר חנינא Rabbi Elazar Bar
Chanina was also earlier, רבי אלעזר בר אבינא. Rabbi Elazar Bar Avina.
Where was רבי אלעזר בר
Rabbi Elazar Bar right before?
No, אמר רבי אלעזר בר אבינא Rabbi Elazar Bar Avina, starts the
גדול מה שנאמר בגבריאל. Gadol mah shene'emar beGabriel. But he also oh
you're right I'm sorry thank you he was the one that said
כל האומר תהילה לדוד. Kol ha'omer tehila leDovid. Yeah I'm sorry I
missed that. Thank you very good point. Right so yes so this
is said because the same one who mentioned אשרי, רבי אלעזר בר
אבינא, is also mentioning this idea about the angels. And the גמרא
Gemara, says תנא, tana, מיכאל באחת גבריאל בשתים, Michael be'achas Gabriel bishtayim,
Michael was with one flying, Gabriel had to do two flyings. אליהו
בארבע, Eliyahu be'arba, Eliyahu was in four. Presumably it means when he's
going to come for the time of to announce the משיח Mashiach
I suppose, but it's very interesting the idea of flying which is
not something I mean Eliyahu was taken up in a whirlwind you
don't normally associate Eliyahu with flying ומלאך המות בשמונה Umalach Hamaves bishmona
and when the angel of death comes it's in eight. ובשעת המגפה
באחת, Ubeshas hamageifa be'achas, but at the time of plague then it's
one, then it's like immediate.
So presumably obviously this is somewhat symbolic you know that meaning death
does not always come very quickly you know it's usually in stages.
Presumably it's saying the same thing about אליהו, Eliyahu, משיח Mashiach is
not going to come suddenly you know all of a sudden everything
is normal and then poof משיח Mashiach comes, it's something that comes
in stages. Maybe not you know hopefully not so many stages but
at least in stages as opposed to the difference between Gabriel and
Michael I'm not sure what that is alluding to. I will also
say by the way the reason it doesn't say Michael in the
first פסוק Pasuk by ישעיהו Yeshayahu is because the names of the
angels Michael and Gabriel whatever only appear in דניאל, Daniel, they only
appear post-exile
and actually the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says it, ירושלמי Yerushalmi says שמות מלאכים
עלו
עמהם מבבל, Shmos malachim alu imahem mibavel, that when they came out
of בבל Bavel after the Babylonian exile back to ארץ ישראל which
is you know which is דניאל Daniel was written at the time
of the exile that's where they started associating angels with personalities and
with names. Prior to that in תנ"ך Tanach you only have them
generically as angels, maybe different categories but the names were something that
was really taken out
בבל Bavel meaning was brought perhaps of the Babylonian culture and that's
actually something that is noted by the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. Okay so now
the גמרא Gemara. continues two lines from the bottom. אמר רבי יהושע
בן לוי, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi, אף על פי שקרא אדם
קריאת שמע בבית הכנסת, Af al pi shekara adam krias Shema beveish
haknesses, ah finally getting back to שמע. Shema Even though a person
has said שמע Shema at shul in the שול, shul, מצוה
לקרותו על מיטתו. Mitzva likroso al mitaso. It is a מצוה mitzvah
to say it right before bedtime, right before you go to sleep.
So this is קריאת שמע על המטה. Krias Shema Al Hamita. אמר
רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yosi, מאי קרא, mai kra, where do you
get it, what פסוק? Pasuk, רגזו ואל תחטאו אמרו בלבבכם על משכבכם
ודומו סלה. Rigzu ve'al techeta'u imru bilvavchem al mishkavchem vedomu sela. Tremble
and do not sin say in your heart on your bed before
lying down and be silent forever. So learning is בלבבכם, bilvavchem, what
do you what's בלבבכם? bilvavchem? Where does בלבבכם bilvavchem appear? The שמע
Shema, is והיו הדברים האלה אשר אנכי מצוך היום על לבבך Vehayu
hadvarim haeileh asher anochi metzavcha hayom al levavecha right? And so it's
על לבבך, al levavecha, לבבכם levavchem is that thing which is on
your heart, the שמע, Shema, say it על משכבכם. al mishkavchem. על
משכבכם ודומו, al mishkavchem v’idomu, you go to sleep. And then be
quiet, then you go to sleep. Now, presumably the reason is because
of רגזו ואל תחטאו, rigzu v’al techetau, not sinning. So framed that
way, we'll see in a minute another way to frame it, it
has to do something about like maybe a concern about sinful thoughts.
Maybe it's a concern and therefore this helps you sort of not
maybe have those thoughts when you're going to sleep. You know the
גמרא Gemara, is often concerned about sexual thoughts and so on, or
maybe it's just an issue about framing your day at the very
beginning and at the very end with the words of שמע, Shema
which is actually what the פסוק pasuk is saying, right? The פסוק
pasuk is בשכבך ובקומך. beshochbecha uvkumecha. And one way you can understand
what's going on here is the גמרא’ס Gemara’s just told us you
don't say the evening שמע Shema right before lying down. You say
the evening שמע Shema on your way home from work when you
go to שול, shul, and after the שמע Shema you say the
שמונה עשרה, then you come home, then you have your meal, then
you go to sleep. So the way we have it in the
liturgy, it's no longer exactly בשכבך. beshochbecha. So now we're telling you,
oh, but say it again right before you go to sleep. Okay,
so one way to understand it is it's really just trying to
maintain the sense of the פסוק pasuk of בשכבך. beshochbecha. But let's
see where the גמרא Gemara goes with this.
Is this talking about dying also?
Possibly, like maybe you'll maybe you'll die, so you'll have said שמע
Shema before you before you pass away as like the last thing.
Could be. I mean, ודומו סלה, v’idomu sela, it seems a little
bit, right, a little silence forever? It sounds a bit it sounds
a little bit like that, yeah.
And we have a whole series of prayers that we say.
Right, so you're going to see some of them alluded to right
now. What's in the night שמע Shema and the- yeah, before you
go- yeah, so some of them are about to be alluded to.
So let's take a
look. אמר רב נחמן אם תלמיד חכם הוא אין צריך. Amar Rav
Nachman im talmid chacham hu ein tzarich. If you're a Torah scholar,
you don't have to say שמע Shema, at night. Why not? So
רש"י Rashi says, if we look at רש"י, Rashi, שרגיל במשנתו לחזור
גרסתו תמיד דיו בכך. sheragil bemishnavo lachazor girsato tamid dayo b’kach. So
you're always learning, so anyway you're probably going to be thinking about
Torah right before going to sleep, which is interesting. It's another idea
of what the פסוק pasuk means, right? ודברת בם בשכבך ובקומך vedibarta
bam beshochbecha uvkumecha couldn't mean שמע, Shema, but it could mean Torah.
You should always be talking about Torah. So the way רש"י’ס Rashi’s
reading it, is you're always thinking and talking about Torah, then you've
got that right before going to sleep as well, so you don't
have to worry about it. אמר אביי אף תלמיד חכם מיבעי ליה
למימר חד פסוקא דרחמי. Amar Abaye af talmid chacham mibayei lei l’meimar
chad pasuka derachamei. Even a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham has to say
one פסוק pasuk of prayer, not maybe of שמע, Shema but of
a type of רחמי. rachamei. רחמי rachamei is a word for prayer.
כגון בידך אפקיד רוחי פדיתה אותי ה' אל אמת. kegon beyadcha afkid
ruchi padita oti Hashem Kel emet. In Your hand, God, I have
trusted, given over my soul, my spirit, the God of truth, that
you recognize the concept of course being that when you go to
sleep, it's your soul is going back to God, and when you
wake up in the morning, it's you're reinsouled. That's why of course
מודה אני לפניך Modeh Ani Lefanecha when you wake up in the
morning. And the idea of קריאת שמע Krias Shema now here is
not just saying שמע Shema, to frame your day, not just saying
שמע, Shema you know, maybe to to direct your thoughts to be
thinking about proper things, but also an acknowledgment that you are sort
of, you know, you're you're losing you know, you're giving over your
soul at night and you're and you're praying to God to get
it back in the next morning. So there's an aspect of prayer
and בקשה bakasha there as well. Yes, Charlie?
It looks like they're driving הלכה halakha from תהלים.
No, they're not driving- oh, you mean from before, רגזו ואל תחטאו?
rigzu v’al techetau? Yeah, but this is not הלכה. halakha. This is
nobody saying it's biblical. This is rabbinic. So if the Rabbis could
legislate, they could certainly take their you know, take their lead from
ideas expressed in פסוקים Psukim, in תהלים. Okay, so here of course
and if you look at קריאת שמע על המטה, Krias Shema Al
Hamita, definitely this idea of God should protect us as we sleep,
and the words of שמע Shema, as a type of a protection
or prayer. You know, I personally, and maybe you know, maybe we'll
talk more about this as well, both issues about מזוזה mezuzah and
so on, you know, I have a you know, I recoil a
little from the idea of like say these things as like some
type of a protection. Like prayer as a protection, yes, you know,
you pray to God to protect you. But as if like the
words protect you, like the מזוזה mezuzah protects your house. To me,
I know there are people that very much believe that, but to
me that feels a little bit too superstitious and too talisman- talismanic,
is that a word? Anyway, so but certainly some of that is
in the you know, could be seen as part of the קריאת
שמע Krias Shema of the nighttime, but at least to frame it
as a prayer that you recognize that, you know, you want God
to protect over your soul and to restore your soul when you
wake up in the morning, that now becomes part of this as
well. אמר רבי לוי בר חמא אמר ריש לקיש לעולם ירגיז אדם
יצר טוב על יצר הרע. Amar Rabi Levi bar Chama Amar Reish
Lakish l’olam yargiz adam yetzer tov al yetzer hara. Before you go
on, again, I know we're behind, but I do need to say
one final thing, which is now we've mentioned קריאת שמע Krias Shema
at night. When we learned the first דף, daf, I did not
mention an important debate or discussion of רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafot.
The very first רש"י Rashi in the מסכת masechta says, why is
it if we're supposed to say שמע, Shema it says the earliest
time is, you know, after nightfall, צאת tzeis and so on, why
is it we say שמע Shema? when it's still well into the
day? We דאוון daven מעריב Maariv when it's still the sun is
over the over the earth. Now, the reason they did that, if
anybody wants to know, there's a good article by Jacob Katz about
why in אשכנז Ashkenaz in אשכנז Ashkenaz they said מעריב Maariv and
they started שבת Shabbat, when it was still light outside. And the
reason has to do because they had very long days and it
didn't get dark till late and also the way the regular society.
And that's also why they דאווענט davened מעריב Maariv, before sunset. So
רש"י Rashi says, okay, so how about שמע? Shema Isn't there a
מצוה mitzvah to say שמע Shema when it gets, when the stars
come out? So רש"י Rashi says, yes, fine, but when we say
שמע Shema again before going to bed, that it's already the right
time and then we're fulfilling our obligation. And that's why the שמע
Shema. at night does double, the bedtime, the קריאת שמע על המטה
Krias Shema Al HaMitta does double service to be יוצא yotze the
מצוה mitzvah of שמע. Shema And a lot of people do that
nowadays, right? They'll דאווען daven an early מעריב, Maariv and some people
will say שמע Shema as soon as the stars come out, but
some people will just say it at the שמע Shema, bedtime and
that's how they'll do their מצוה. mitzvah. רש"י Rashi says one paragraph
is enough. That'll be a discussion later, how many paragraphs are biblically
obligations. People that, you know, a lot of people that דאווען daven
מעריב Maariv. early say it again at that time, they say all
three paragraphs. That's what רש"י Rashi says. But תוספות Tosfos takes offense.
תוספות Tosfos says: what do you mean? The מצוה mitzvah of שמע,
Shema that's the bedtime שמע Shema in fact, and the מצוה mitzvah
of שמע Shema has to be with the ברכות. brachos. And therefore
it has to be the שמע Shema we're doing at מעריב. Maariv
So תוספות Tosfos has a way of arguing that because you can
דאווען daven מעריב Maariv, before sunset, you might know that there's that
הלכה halacha we'll find out about it later, that defines the time
enough as night to also say that you can fulfill שמע Shema
at that time as well. The reason this is significant is because
it goes onto this theme I'm discussing with you about the שמע
Shema as an independent מצוה mitzvah and שמע Shema as part of
the liturgy. For תוספות Tosfos it is key that number one, the
מצוה mitzvah of שמע Shema. occur with the ברכות brachos of שמע.
Shema He cannot imagine doing the ברכות brachos of שמע Shema without
it being the מצוה mitzvah of שמע Shema. and that the מצוה
mitzvah comes later. And that תוספות Tosfos also argues that because it's
a good time for דאווענינג davening מעריב, Maariv it's a good time
for saying שמע. Shema Even though nobody's going to sleep now. So
for תוספות, Tosfos, the שמע Shema in the liturgy is very connected,
you know, becomes the מצוה mitzvah שמע Shema becomes very connected to
how it exists within the liturgy. Whereas for רש"י Rashi you could
really be independent. We tend to go like רש"י Rashi and if
we דאווען daven an early מעריב we say שמע Shema again when
the stars come out. Or at right before bedtime, yes. I was
saying that according to תוספות, Tosfos, שמע Shema. doesn't need to be
repeated? That's what תוספות Tosfos says. I mean you repeat it for
קריאת שמע על המטה Krias Shema Al HaMitta but not for the
מצוה mitzvah of שמע. Shema We don't rule that way. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara goes on. Four lines from the top. אמר
רבי לוי בר חמא אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש: Amar Rabbi Levi
bar Chama amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish: לעולם ירגיז אדם יצר הטוב
על יצר הרע. L'olam yargiz adam yeitzer hatov al yeitzer hara. You
should always be fighting, your taking your good inclination and doing battle
against your evil inclination. Meaning don't wait till temptation presents itself that
you have to then struggle to be resisting your desires, you know,
you should always be working on your מדות middos so even, you
know, use your good inclination to do battle against your, you know,
your baser inclinations. שנאמר, Shene'emar, רגזו ואל תחטאו. Rigzu v'al techeta'u. Tremble
and do not sin. So presumably you do the trembling and the
fighting, רוגז rogez also because... ירגיז yargiz also can be like to
fight, you know, to struggle beforehand so you don't sin when temptation
presents itself. אם נצחו מוטב. Im nitzcho, mutav. If you have been
victorious, good. ואם לאו, V'im lav, and if that doesn't work just
working on your מדות middos directly, יעסוק בתורה. yaasok baTorah. Learn תורה.
Torah. That can also help to change, meaning sometimes the indirect way
is approach, work on, you know, strengthening your good character rather than
on directly attacking, you know, your baser inclinations. So learn תורה, Torah,
שנאמר Shene'emar, אמרו בלבבכם, Imru bilvavchem, say on your hearts, right, על
לבבכם, al levavchem, which also is not just talking about שמע Shema.
but also could be talking about תורה. Torah. אם נצחו מוטב. Im
nitzcho, mutav. If that, if that is enough to be victorious, good.
ואם לאו, V'im lav, יקרא קריאת שמע. yikra Krias Shema. Then say
שמע. Shema שנאמר shene'emar, על משכבכם, Al mishkavchem, the thing you say
before going to bed. Not exactly clear to me how the saying
of שמע Shema. is going to be more practically effective than the
learning of תורה, Torah, but anyway, that's what he says as the
next stage. So תורה Torah and then שמע. Shema אם נצחו מוטב.
Im nitzcho, mutav. If you win, good. ואם לאו, V'im lav, יזכור
לו יום המיתה. yizkor lo yom hamisa. You remind your יצר הרע
yetzer hara or yourself about the fact that you will eventually die
and sort of the transient nature of this world and presumably also
that you're going to have to stand in judgment before God and
hopefully that'll help keep you on the right path. שנאמר, shene'emar, and
here's what James referred to before, ודמו סלה, V'domu sela, be silent
forever. So again this is a parsing of the verse and the
idea of a period when we'll all be silent and we'll be
in the grave. Hopefully that will keep you serious-minded enough that you'll
be able to control yourself and not sin. So again, I don't
know exactly getting into a broader sense about working to develop our
character, I'm not exactly sure how שמע Shema becomes more effective in
this sense than the general learning of תורה. Torah. Is this about
character development or perhaps is this an allusion to sexual temptation? יצר
ה... yetzer ha... well יצר הרע yetzer hara is pre... I mean
it is true that a sort of maybe classic, you know, expression
of יצר הרע yetzer hara is very much in terms of sexual,
sexual desire but it's not limited to that. It's more broad. But
why are you saying that? How do you see that? על משכבכם.
Al mishkavchem. Because if you look if you look at the the...
Oh I see. You're saying so maybe maybe you're about to so
maybe you're about to have a... so you're about to do a
sexual sin and that's why it's the שמע Shema before going to
bed. So if you say the שמע Shema right before you're about
to have to do what you're about to do, then... help set
you straight? Is that the way you're reading it? Presumably if these
sexual encounters happening. Oh, that's interesting. Meaning I was trying, I was
reading it as לעולם, Le'olam, you should always be doing this, so
it's an ongoing battle with the יצר הרע Yetzer Hara and something
you do prior to temptation. You're reading it sort of at the
moment of. Okay. Yeah. How does one do that without תורה Torah
and קריאת שמע? Kriyat Shema? Well, you could, you could do that,
oh I see, you're saying like if you learn מוסר Musar and
other types of things, doesn't that involve תורה Torah and יום המיתה?
Yom Hamita? It could, it could. Yeah, well that's also a good
question. Yeah, it doesn't give you that type of an advice. That's
a good question. So I guess we could ask the בעלי מוסר
Ba'alei Musar that, but the גמרא Gemara is just giving you a
mandate. All right, so ואמר רב לוי בר חמא אמר רבי שמעון
בן לקיש, Ve'amar Rav Levi bar Chama amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish,
מאי דכתיב, Mai dichtiv, what's meant by the פסוק, pasuk ואתנה לך
את לוחות האבן והתורה והמצוה אשר כתבתי להורותם? Ve'etnah lecha et luchot
ha'even vehatorah vehamitzvah asher katavti lehorotam? This is again the same speaker,
רב לוי בר חמא, Rav Levi bar Chama, he was the one
who dealt with this פסוק which we say by שמע Shema, at
bedtime. And now here's another teaching of his. What is meant by
the verse ואתנה לך את לוחות האבן והתורה והמצוה אשר כתבתי להורותם,
Ve'etnah lecha et luchot ha'even vehatorah vehamitzvah asher katavti lehorotam, I have
given to you the tablets of stone and the Torah and the
commandment that I have written to teach them? So לוחות, Luchot, אלו
עשרת הדברות, Elu Aseret Hadibrot, so the לוחות Luchot is of course
the tablets, the Ten Commandments. תורה, Torah, זה מקרא, Ze Mikra, it's
פסוקים, Psukim it's the written Torah. והמצוה, Vehamitzvah, זו משנה, Zu Mishnah,
which is interesting. Why is מצוה Mitzvah משנה? Mishnah? Because apparently משנה
Mishnah is very much, although you don't actually פסקן Pasken from משנה,
Mishnah, משנה Mishnah is very much straight laws. Here's a הלכה Halacha
here, here's a הלכה Halacha here, sometimes it's debated, but it's very
much focused on just telling me what my obligations are and the
parameters of my obligations. So that's מצוה. Mitzvah. אשר כתבתי, Asher katavti,
אלו נביאים וכתובים, Elu Nevi'im uchetuvim, other things were sort of part
of the כתובים Ktuvim of the holy script, not just the Torah
but the נביאים Nevi'im and the כתובים, Ktuvim, the prophets and the
later writings. להורותם, Lehorotam, זו גמרא. Zu Gemara. That is already the
גמרא, Gemara the what we're doing, you know, it's not just the
straight laws but it's the argumentation, the analysis, the discussion. That is
what you need ultimately to get to הוראה Hora'ah to be able
to give rulings over, you know, on new issues and on unclear
issues. To be הוראה Hora'ah requires גמרא. Gemara Now all of that
is in this פסוק that God says I have given it to
you Moshe מהר סיני. Mehar Sinai. So מלמד, Melamed, this teaches us
שכולם ניתנו למשה מסיני. Shekulam nitnu le-Moshe mi-Sinai. Everything was given to
Moshe, פסוקים, psukim, the later נביאים, Nevi'im, the משנה, Mishnah, the גמרא,
Gemara, it was all given to Moshe מסיני. Mi-Sinai. So this is
part of a, I will just say and it's a theme I
actually mentioned on שבת, you know, there's two general schools of thought
about this whole idea about our tradition, whether everything was given to
Moshe and we're just sort of discovering what was already given, or
whether, you know, the written Torah was given to Moshe and the
rabbis or the בית דין Beit Din or whatever were empowered to
interpret the Torah and they had certain principles of how to interpret
and a lot of at least the oral law was not directly
given but was derived later and they were authorized to derive it
but it ultimately was a human endeavor of encountering the text and
of deriving the oral law. So there are some that speak very
much as if it was all given and all just handed down
and others that speak very much in the other direction. There's obviously
ways you could reconcile, what does it mean to all be given?
All be given means that it was given in potential because we
are given the ability to derive it and therefore in certain ways,
it's like the story where Moshe is in the back of the
בית מדרש Beit Midrash of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and he doesn't
know what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is talking about, how you got
all of this out of his Torah, and then at the end
somebody says רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva where you know this from? And
he says הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai. So there are ways
in which it is all derived and it is all given למשה
מסיני. Le-Moshe mi-Sinai. Anyway this is one passage which emphasizes that it
is all direct from סיני. Sinai. Now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר
רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak, כל הקורא קריאת שמע על מיטתו, Kol
hakoreh Kriyat Shema al mitato, we're back to קריאת שמע על המיטה,
Kriyat Shema al hamita, so here we're going to see some of
the פסוקים that we have in our קריאת שמע על המיטה. Kriyat
Shema al hamita. Whoever says קריאת שמע Kriyat Shema at bed כאילו
אוחז חרב של שתי פיפיות בידו, Ke'ilu ochez cherev shel shtei pifiyot
beyado, it's like holding a two-edged sword in his hand, שנאמר, shene'emar,
רוממות אל בגרונם וחרב פיפיות בידם, Romemot El bigronam vecherev pifiyot beyadam,
the praising of God is in their throats and a two-edged sword
in their hands. מאי משמע, Mai mashma, where do you get that
it has to do with קריאת שמע? Kriyat Shema? אמר מר זוטרא
ואיתימא רב אשי, Amar Mar Zutra ve'itayma Rav Ashi, מרישא דעניינא, Merisha
de'inyana, from the beginning of the discussion. דכתיב, it says in the
earlier פסוק, יעלזו חסידים בכבוד ירננו על משכבותם, Ya'alzu chasidim bechavod yeranenu
al mishkevotam, the righteous ones will rejoice in honor, they will, they
will rejoice on their beds. ואחר כך כתיב, Ve'achar kach ktiv, then
it says, רוממות אל בגרונם וחרב פיפיות בידם. Romemot El bigronam vecherev
pifiyot beyadam. So what's on their beds? The קריאת שמע Kriyat Shema
they say at their beds and that gives them a two-edged sword.
Who needs a two-edged sword? So now we are getting into another
function of קריאת שמע Kriyat Shema which is not just God watch
over me, you know, bring, you know, give me back my soul
in next morning, but also the sense of the evil spirits that
might be out at night and the need of protection from those.
Therefore this gives you a two-edged sword against them. ואמר רבי יצחק,
Ve'amar Rabbi Yitzchak, אמר רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak, כל הקורא קריאת
שמע על מיטתו, Kol hakoreh Kriyat Shema al mitato, מזיקין בדילין הימנו.
Mazikin bedilin heimenu. So if it wasn't clear enough, now it's clear,
clear enough until now, it's clear now. And the sons of רשף,
reshef, which is a word we're going to say means the מזיקין,
mazikin, יגביהו עוף, yagbihu uf, will give forth flight, will fly away.
ואין עוף אלא תורה, ve'ein uf ela Torah, and there's no flight,
עוף uf here means תורה. Torah. They will be, they will remove
because of עוף, uf, because of תורה. Torah. שנאמר התעיף עיניך בו
ואיננו. shene'emar hatyaif einecha bo v'einenu. If you sort of flutter your
eye away from it, it will no longer be there. So תורה,
Torah, it's another פסוק about how important it
is to constantly be learning and reviewing תורה Torah because you distract
yourself from it
and all of a sudden you forget it and it's lost from
you. But here we say, ah, so you see at least it's
in the word עוף uf is in the context of תורה. Torah.
ואין רשף אלא מזיקין, ve'ein reshef ela mazikin, and רשף reshef means
the מזיקין. mazikin. שנאמר מזי רעב ולחמי רשף וקטב מרירי. shene'emar mizeh
ra'av ulichumei reshef veketev meriri. Part of the קללה, klalah, the curse
in דברים, Devarim, where it speaks about famine and it says ולחמי
רשף, ulichumei reshef, so רשף reshef here is understood to mean being
somehow attacked by these מזיקין mazikin that are called רשף. reshef. So
if you learn תורה, Torah, specifically here interpreted as שמע, Shema then
you will be protected from the מזיקין. mazikin. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar
Reish Lakish, כל העוסק בתורה יסורין בדילין הימנו. kol haosek baTorah yissurin
bdilin heimenu. Anybody who learns תורה, Torah, now let's not just worry
about מזיקין mazikin and let's not just worry about going to saying
שמע bedtime, but in general how תורה Torah protects you. Anybody who
learns תורה, Torah, afflictions separate from you, you won't be afflicted. שנאמר
ובני רשף יגביהו עוף. shene'emar u'vnei reshef yagbihu uf. So the בני
רשף bnei reshef will be lifted up by עוף. uf. ואין עוף
אלא תורה, ve'ein uf ela Torah, עוף uf is תורה. Torah. שנאמר
התעיף עיניך בו ואיננו. shene'emar hatyaif einecha bo v'einenu. ואין רשף אלא
יסורין, ve'ein reshef ela yissurin, now רשף reshef is no longer just
specifically מזיקין mazikin but it's יסורין. yissurin. שנאמר מזי רעב ולחמי רשף.
shene'emar mizeh ra'av ulichumei reshef. So the point is רעב ra'av is
hunger, קטב מרירי ketev meriri is understood to be another type of
מזיק, mazik, and רשף reshef appears between hunger and מזיק. mazik. So
you can interpret them as a type of hunger, a type of
normal affliction, or as a type of מזיק. mazik. So the first
one interprets it as a type of מזיק, mazik, it'll protect you
from מזיק, mazik, and this interprets in terms of יסורין. yissurin. Now,
the מזיק mazik you understand a little better. You know, you think
that there's these some supernatural creatures, so somehow learning תורה Torah will
give you supernatural protection. But saying that it protects you from יסורין
yissurin starts to bring up questions about, you know, about צדיק ורע
לו, tzaddik v'ra lo, רשע וטוב לו, rasha v'tov lo, like oh,
if you learn תורה, Torah, nothing bad is going to happen, you
won't be beset by afflictions. Is that really true? So let's take
a look because the גמרא Gemara picks up on this. So let's
see where the גמרא Gemara goes. אמר ליה רבי יוחנן, amar leh
Rabbi Yochanan, הא אפילו תינוקות של בית רבן יודעים אותה. ha afilu
tinokos shel beis raban yodin osah. The fact that תורה Torah protects
you from affliction, even like חדר cheder kids, you know, know this.
It's, you know, you learn it when you learn פסוקים, when you
learn תורה Torah and you know in, you know, in first grade.
שנאמר, shene'emar, the פסוק says, והיה אם שמוע תשמע לקול ה׳ אלקיך,
vehayah im shamoa tishma lekol Hashem Elokecha, if you listen to the
voice of God, והישר בעיניו תעשה, vehayashar beeinav taaseh, do what's right,
והאזנת למצותיו ושמרת כל חקיו, vehaazanta l'mitzvotav veshamarta kol chukav, and you
give ear to the מצות mitzvot and you observe all the commandments,
כל המחלה אשר שמתי במצרים לא אשים עליך כי אני ה׳ רפאך.
kol hamachalah asher samti beMitzrayim lo asim alecha ki ani Hashem rofe'echa.
All the bad things I put on Egypt I won't put on
you because I am God that heals you. So you see if
you listen to מצות mitzvot and you do תורה, Torah, yeah, you'll
be protected, bad things won't happen to you.
I don't need to learn it from this פסוק of בני רשף.
bnei reshef. אלא, here's what that פסוק is telling me, כל שאפשר
לו לעסוק בתורה ואינו עוסק. kol she'efshar lo la'asok baTorah v'eino osek.
It's worse. It's not just that תורה Torah will protect you, but
if you have the potential to learn תורה Torah and you're not
availing yourself of that, of
that opportunity, הקדוש ברוך הוא, Hakadosh Baruch Hu, מביא עליו יסורין מכוערין
ועוכרין אותו. meivi alav yissurin mechoarin ve'ochin oso.
God will bring onto you sort of harsh afflictions and they will
sort of and they will stir you up, they will afflict you.
שנאמר, as the פסוק says, נאלמתי דומיה החשיתי מטוב. ne'elamti dumiyah hechashaiti
mitov. I have been silent, דומיה dumiyah is also silent, anyway, I
have... so if you are silent, you are not
learning תורה, Torah, then you will be lacking good.
Not just are you lacking the good, but וכאבי נעכר, uche'eivi ne'echar,
my wounds have been troubled, have been, have been afflicted. ואין טוב
אלא תורה. ve'ein tov ela Torah. If you're silent from טוב, tov,
טוב tov is תורה. Torah. שנאמר, so החשיתי מטוב, hechashaiti mitov, I've
been silent from good, not just it
doesn't just mean good things don't happen to me, but I've been
silent
from learning the good things. שנאמר, כי לקח טוב נתתי לכם, she-ne'emar
ki lekach tov natati lachem, I have given you a good taking,
a good thing, a good a good gift,
תורתי אל תעזבו, Torasi al taazovu,
do not abandon my תורה. Torah. So here we are saying it's
not so... it's not just that תורה Torah protects you from bad
things, but it's actually even a little worse that if you have
the opportunity to learn תורה Torah and you don't, then you actually
will be afflicted. So it's a world now that works very sort
of straightforwardly in terms of reward and punishment. If you do the
right thing you're protected, you do the wrong thing you're punished, and
even in that gray area where you're not exactly doing the wrong
thing but you're not doing as good as you can. Everything works
very much according to this divine economy. So let's take a look
at how the גמרא Gemara is clearly aware that it doesn't always
work out that way. So the גמרא Gemara continues: אמר רבי לוי
ואיתימא רבי חנינא בר פפא, Amar Rabbi Levi ve-eima lei Rabbi Hanina
bar Pappa, בא וראה שלא כמידת הקדוש ברוך הוא מידת בשר ודם.
Bo u-re'ei she-lo ke-middat HaKadosh Baruch Hu middat basar va-dam. First we
want to say something about this פסוק of כי לקח טוב. ki
lekach tov. Come and see that the way of God is not
like the way of flesh and blood. מידת בשר ודם אדם מוכר
חפץ לחברו, Middat basar va-dam adam mocher chefetz le-chavero, מוכר עצב ולוקח
שמח. mocher atzev ve-lokei-ach samei-ach. If you normally you sell something to
your friend, you're sad, and your friend who buys it is happy.
Now, of course it's a very bizarre thing to say if you're
in business. But the point is, in the time of the גמרא,
Gemara commerce was not their main way of making a living, so
you did not buy, so when you sold things you were selling
more household items. You sold things because you needed to put food
on the table, so you had to sell your car, you had
to sell something that meant something to you, you know, that you
really needed but you needed the money. So in that type of
a situation, you're sad that you have to give it up, this
is something that is dear, and the other person is happy that
they have it. ולוקח שמח. ve-lokei-ach samei-ach. אבל הקדוש ברוך הוא אינו
כן, Aval HaKadosh Baruch Hu eino kein, God is not this way.
נתן להם תורה לישראל ושמח, Natan la-hem Torah le-Yisrael ve-samach, he gave
the תורה Torah to the Jewish people, which is obviously something very
dear, and he was joyous, שנאמר כי לקח טוב נתתי לכם, ki
lekach tov nasati lachem, look, I have given you this wonderful thing,
תורתי אל תעזובו, Torati al ta'azovu, know how good it is, do
not abandon my תורה. Torah. So obviously there's this sense of God
being very happy about this exchange and taking joy in it. And
of course the idea being that, you know, it's like when you
give something to your children, you're very happy to give them something
that's important and maybe you pass on something that's very dear, you
want them to have it because of how significant, because of how
much it means to you, because they also mean a great deal
to you as well and you want to be sharing in this
very significant object and in this thing that is being given over.
So here's the sense that God is giving it to us but
he's happy because of the power that תורה Torah has for us
and because of his relationship with us. Okay. So we'll just take
that to the whole creation I would say. Yeah, the joy of
ה' Hashem to do the creation I mean. Oh, to create the
world. Yeah, the sense that that's a gift and that right, and
that gets into interesting questions about, right, about sort of God as
a giver and like according to some Jewish thinkers, the reason that
God created the world was because the nature of a good God
is to do good for others and that that's so, so that's
the full expression of what of God's goodness. Yes, this question, you
get the feeling in a way that we're being spoken to as
if we're children. Aha, in other words, you won't necessarily love and
believe unless there's a downside of being punished. Well okay, but that
is true throughout the תורה, Torah, you know, the idea of reward
and punishment and the גמרא Gemara here is just reflecting it. So
it certainly is not rabbinic theology, it's biblical theology. Right. So that's
always the question about שלא לשמה she-lo lishma and לשמה, lishma, meaning
this sort of שלא לשמה she-lo lishma motivations, the external motivations, and
then doing things because they're intrinsically the right thing and very often
people, ideally you'd like to, people should be doing it for the
right reasons, but unfortunately sometimes people need the other types of motivation.
So let's take a look a little bit more at the גמרא
Gemara before we have to end for today. Okay. אמר רב ואיתימא
רב חסדא אם ראה אדם שיסורין באין עליו, Amar Rav ve-eima lei
Rav Chisda im ra'ah adam she-yissurin ba'im alav, now here we get
to be focusing exactly on this about afflictions as punishment. If a
person sees that afflictions are coming on him and he's beginning to
start things are starting to, you know, bad things are starting to
happen, so try to sort of reverse the course, what should you
do? יפשפש במעשיו. yefashpesh be-ma'asav. You should investigate your deeds because maybe
it's because of some sin that you've done that they're happening and
do תשובה, teshuva, use this as an opportunity to do תשובה, teshuva,
שנאמר נחפשה דרכינו ונחקורה, she-ne'emar nachpasa deracheinu ve-nachkora, let us search out
our paths and investigate. And then somehow the גירסא girsa here, פשפש
ומצא, pishpesh ve-matza, if you investigated it and you found what you
have done wrong, יעשה תשובה, ya'aseh teshuva, then do תשובה, teshuva, שנאמר
ונשובה עד ה', she-ne'emar ve-nashuva ad Hashem, and then we return to
God. פשפש ולא מצא, pishpesh ve-lo matza, if you investigated and you
could not find any particular sin that you think is deserving of
this, יתלה בביטול תורה, yitleh be-vittel Torah, goes back to the point
we made before. Sometimes it's not just sins of commission, sometimes it's
sins of omission. Maybe you haven't been learning enough תורה, Torah, שנאמר
אשרי הגבר אשר תיסרנו יה, she-ne'emar ashrei hagever asher teyassrennu yah, praise
is the man that God will afflict him, ומתורתך תלמדנו, u-mi-Toratecha telamdennu,
and teach us from your תורה. Torah. So presumably it means that
as a result of these יסורין yissurin that leads to learning תורה
Torah because it is a spur for us to realize that we
have not been learning תורה Torah as much as we could be.
ואם תלה ולא מצא, ve-im talah ve-lo matza, if you said yeah
maybe it is based on תורה Torah but it didn't make sense,
either you've been learning תורה Torah great or it was not proportional,
somehow it could not be attributed to that, בידוע, beyadu'a, then you
should know, and here becomes the question, what happens when you're suffering
and there's no explanation for it? So here’s the classic answer, at
least this גמרא Gemara gives: יסורין של אהבה הם, Yisurin shel ahava
heim, afflictions of love they are, שנאמר כי את אשר יאהב ה׳
יוכיח, Shene’emar ki et asher ye’ehav Hashem yochiach, those that God loves,
God will remonstrate. Now this idea is, you know, a very challenging
one, as obviously here, what’s beautiful about this גמרא Gemara before you
get to the answer is the implicit question, right? חז״ל Chazal are
not happy enough just to say, oh yeah, the תורה Torah says
the good get rewarded, the bad get punished, that’s the way the
world works. Sort of knows that the world doesn’t work that way,
and it’s sort of, and it’s asking, it’s not sort of express
saying it as a question but that’s the implicit, and later in
another דף daf or two, the גמרא Gemara will explicitly say משה
Moshe challenged God: why do the, you know, the bad have it
good and the good have it bad? That’s part of like the
implicit question here, why do people suffer if they don’t deserve to?
And first we try to find ways, well, sometimes it’s not always
about really bad things, sometimes it’s about, you know, more things you
could have been doing better, but sometimes there is no explanation, and
the way the גמרא Gemara does explain it is יסורין של אהבה.
Yisurin shel ahava. Now what’s that mean, afflictions of love? רש״י Rashi
says, this is again sort of part of this divine, you know,
accounting, which is, you know, because you suffered in this world, you
get more reward in the world to come. So, yes, you’re not
suffering to pay off any sin, but to increase your reward in
the world to come. But the גמרא doesn’t really tell us what
יסורין של אהבה Yisurin shel ahava means, it just says יסורין של
אהבה. Yisurin shel ahava. You could look at it also as a
type of a way of, you know, development of character, you could
say a test like אברהם, Avraham, but even if it’s not like
a test to pass, but you know a sense that, you know,
people that can deal with affliction and, you know, certainly it’s like
creates like a, you know, strengthens their character in general and their
religious character and so on, that they’re able to live, you know,
to deal with those types of challenges. Again, you know, as we’ll
see, some people say, you know, save me the development of character,
who needs the יסורין? yisurin? And the גמרא is going to get
to that, but it is a very, it is a classic answer,
but an answer that is often not unpacked really, you know, how,
and is it a way that really we can understand what יסורין
של אהבה Yisurin shel ahava are? The גמרא is go, if you
want to hear more about that, I’ll just say that tonight at
the סיום, Siyum, which I hope I’ll see all of you there,
we’re going to have one of the classes will be from ירדנה
קופ-יוסף, Yardena Cope-Yosef, who teaches דף יומי Daf Yomi at מתן Matan
in Israel, is going to be giving a class on exactly this
topic called Pains of Love, so יסורין של אהבה, Yisurin shel ahava,
so you can hear what she has to say about that. Let’s
just read one more line and then we’ll end for today. Okay,
where is it? Okay, שנאמר כי את אשר... Shene’emar ki et asher...
אמר רבא אמר רב סחורה אמר רב הונא: Amar Rava amar Rav
Sechora amar Rav Huna: כל שהקדוש ברוך הוא חפץ בו, Kol she’Hakadosh
Baruch Hu chafetz bo, anyone that God desires, that has love for,
מדכאו ביסורין, medake’o beyisurin, tramples him down with afflictions, שנאמר וה׳ חפץ
דכאו החלי. shene’emar vaHashem chafetz dake’o hechali. God, the one that God
has desired, the way this is reading it, He has trampled him
down with sickness. יכול אפילו לא קבלם מאהבה, Yachol afilu lo kiblam
me’ahava, and this is the last point I want to end on:
maybe even if they were not accepted with love? Someone says, who
needs these afflictions? How do you know that God is only going
to do this, or maybe how do you know they’ll only have
this value if you accept them with love? תלמוד לומר אם תשים
אשם נפשו, Talmud lomar im tasim asham nafsho, if you place your
soul as an אשם, asham, maybe meaning an אשם asham is like
a guilt offering. Here read it as: מה אשם לדעת, mah asham
lada’at, the same way when you bring a sin offering it atones
for you if you bring it consciously with intent, אף יסורין לדעת.
af yisurin lada’at. So these יסורין yisurin either will only be brought
or will have their significance when they are accepted intentionally and willingly.
ואם קיבלם מה שכרו, Ve’im kiblam mah secharo, if you accept them,
what is your reward? יראה זרע יאריך ימים, Yireh zera ya’arich yamim,
you will see seed, you will lengthen days. ולא עוד, Velo od,
not only that, אלא שתלמודו מתקיים בידו, ela she’talmudo mitkayem beyado, your
תורה Torah will be fulfilled in your hand, שנאמר וחפץ ה׳ בידו
יצלח, shene’emar vechafetz Hashem beyado yitzlach, the one that God desired, which
was the phrase we had before, will be successful in his hand.
So as we end, I just want to say one final point
about this, which is sort of accepting them with intention, that so
much about this is how we interpret what is happening to us.
For example, there’s a גמרא that says, you know, that what is
an example of יסורין של אהבה, Yisurin shel ahava, even if like
you stick your hand in your pocket to get change and you
stick, stuck it in the wrong pocket and you come out with
the wrong change, that’s like יסורין של אהבה, Yisurin shel ahava, not
so bad. So הרב סולובייצ'יק HaRav Soloveitchik said it’s יסורין של אהבה
Yisurin shel ahava if you treat it as יסורין של אהבה. Yisurin
shel ahava. You know, if you sort of see these things as
part of your relationship with God and you use it as an
opportunity to reflect on, maybe I should be doing things better, maybe
I should be pushing myself more, like the גמרא says, to investigate,
to reflect, maybe the very fact that יסורין yisurin cause you to
engage in this act of self-reflection about how to improve yourself and
what you’re doing right, ultimately that is part of, that’s what partly
makes it, you know, יסורין של אהבה. Yisurin shel ahava. That’s partly
what sort of is all about straightening your way and your relationship
to God. If that’s not how you interpret it, you interpret it
as just why are these terrible things happening to me, then they’re
not יסורין של אהבה. Yisurin shel ahava. Whether they happen to you
or not is not necessarily clear, but they’re not יסורין של אהבה.
Yisurin shel ahava. Okay, we will continue with this tomorrow. I don't
know how we're going to catch up. Maybe we'll skip some pieces
if I don't catch up. Okay, let's try to finish this part
over here. אמר רב הונא Amar Rav Huna כל המבקר חולה kol
ha-mevaker choleh one who visits the sick נוטל אחד מששים בצערו notel
echad mi-shishim be-tza'aro takes away one-sixtieth of his suffering. אמרו לו Amru
lo they said to him אם כן im ken if so ליקו
שיתין leiku shitin let sixty people visit him וליוקמוהו ve-lyokmuhu and they'll
stand him up. אמר לו Amar lo he said to them כעשירית
של פירות ke-asirit shel peirot it's like a tenth of the fruit,
meaning a sixtieth of what is currently there. This is also a
גמרא in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia on דף ל'. daf lamed. רב
פפא חלש Rav Papa chalash Rav Papa was sick. על לגביה רב
שימי בר אשי Al legabeih Rav Shimi bar Ashi Rav Shimi bar
Ashi went to visit him. חזא דתקיף ליה עלמא Chaza de-takif leih
alma he saw it was getting difficult for him. אמר להו Amar
lehu he said to them ליהוי רחמי עליה le-hevei rachamei aleih pray
for him. רבי יוחנן חלש Rabbi Yochanan chalash Rabbi Yochanan was sick.
על לגביה רבי חנינא Al legabeih Rabbi Chanina Rabbi Chanina came to
visit him. אמר ליה Amar leih he said to him חביבין עליך
ייסורין chavivin alecha yissurin are sufferings beloved to you? אמר ליה Amar
leih he said to him לא הן ולא שכרן lo hen velo
secharan not them and not their reward. אמר ליה Amar leih he
said to him הב לי ידך hav li yadecha give me your
hand. יהב ליה ידיה ואוקמיה Yahav leih yadeih ve-okmeih he gave him
his hand and he stood him up. רבי חייא בר אבא חלש
Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba chalash Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba was sick. על
לגביה רבי יוחנן Al legabeih Rabbi Yochanan Rabbi Yochanan went to visit
him. אמר ליה Amar leih he said to him חביבין עליך ייסורין?
chavivin alecha yissurin? אמר ליה Amar leih he said to him לא
הן ולא שכרן. lo hen velo secharan. אמר ליה Amar leih הב
לי ידך. hav li yadecha. יהב ליה ידיה ואוקמיה. Yahav leih yadeih
ve-okmeih. אמאי? Amai? Why did he need help? לוקים רבי יוחנן לנפשיה
Lokim Rabbi Yochanan lenafsheih let Rabbi Yochanan stand himself up. אמרי Amri
they say אין חבוש מתיר עצמו מבית האסורים ein chavush matir atzmo
mi-beit ha-asurim a prisoner cannot release himself from prison. רבי אלעזר חלש
Rabbi Elazar chalash Rabbi Elazar was sick. על לגביה רבי יוחנן Al
legabeih Rabbi Yochanan Rabbi Yochanan went to visit him. חזא דהוה קא
גני בבית אפל Chaza de-hava ka ganei be-veit afal he saw he
was lying in
a dark room. גלייה לדרעיה ונפל נהורא Galyeih le-daraeih venafal
nehora he uncovered his arm and there was light. חזייה דהוה קא
בכי רבי אלעזר Chazyeih de-hava ka bachi Rabbi Elazar he saw he
was crying. אמר ליה Amar leih he said to him אמאי קא
בכית? amai ka bachit? Why are you crying? אי משום תורה דלא
פשת? ei mishum Torah dela pashat? שנינו shaninu אחד המרבה ואחד הממעיט
ובלבד שיכוין לבו לשמים. echad ha-marbeh ve-echad ha-mameit u-vilvad she-yechaven libo la-shamayim.
אי משום מזוני? ei mishum mezonei? לא כל אדם זוכה לשתי שלחנות.
lo kol adam zocheh li-shnei shulchanot. אי משום בני? ei mishum benei?
דין גירמא דעשיראה ביר. dein girma de-asira'ah bir. אמר ליה Amar leih
להאי שופרא דבלי בארעא קא בכינא le-hai shufra de-vali be-ara'a ka bachina
I am crying for this beauty that will eventually rot in the
ground. אמר ליה Amar leih he said to him על דא ודאי
קא בכית al da vadai ka bachit for this you should indeed
cry. ובכו תרוייהו u-vacho tarvaihu they both cried. אמר ליה Amar leih
חביבין עליך ייסורין? chavivin alecha yissurin? אמר ליה Amar leih לא הן
ולא שכרן. lo hen velo secharan. אמר ליה Amar leih הב לי
ידך. hav li yadecha. יהב ליה ידיה ואוקמיה. Yahav leih yadeih ve-okmeih.